(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners,
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we're gonna be bringing
you a very useful lesson about being sick.
- Yeah, we're going to
learn how to tell your boss
that you can't go to
work because you're sick.
- Exactly, this is really important
because we all get sick and
sometimes you just can't go to work.
- Yes.
- Or maybe sometimes you
just don't want to go to work.
- Exactly, maybe you're lying.
- Yeah.
- But we're gonna be teaching
you how to do it anyways.
So before we start with our dialogue,
let's take a look at vocabulary preview.
- Vocabulary preview.
- In this vocabulary preview,
we have two words for you.
The first one is quite ill.
- Quite ill.
- So quite ill.
- Very sick.
- Quite is a synonym of very.
- Exactly.
- Okay.
- Yeah.
- Sick.
- They both mean the
same thing, no difference.
- No difference at all.
I just think ill is more
common in British English.
- Mm, exactly.
All right, let's take a look
at our second word, flu.
- The flu.
So the flu is a virus.
- Yeah, it's a sickness.
- Okay, and it's very similar to a cold.
- Yes, but just a lot worse.
- A lot worse.
So it's stronger.
- Yeah, yeah.
It's also called influenza.
- So the flu.
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay, so let's listen to our dialogue.
What's gonna happen here today?
- Well, we're going to listen as Julie
calls her boss to tell him she's sick.
- All right, but is she really sick?
- I don't know.
- Let's find out.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, Daniel speaking,
how might help you?
- Hi, Daniel.
Julie, hey, (coughs)
- Well, hi, Julie, how are you?
- Actually, I'm feeling quite ill today.
- Oh, I'm sorry to hear that.
What's wrong?
- I think I'm coming down with the flu.
I have a headache, a sore throat, a runny
nose, and I'm feeling slightly feverish.
- Let's see, so you're calling in sick.
- Yes, I was hoping to
take the day off to recover.
- Okay, then, try and get some rest.
(upbeat music)
- All right, so Julie didn't
really seem to be sick, huh?
- Yeah, I don't know.
That cough was just a little too much.
- It seemed like she was acting.
- Yeah.
- All right, so let's take a look at some
of this vocabulary in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
We have five words for you here,
and these are all great words
to describe a sickness, right?
All right, the first one, headache.
- Headache.
So when you have a headache,
you have a sore head, right?
- Right, your head hurts.
- So it's pretty simple.
- Yep.
- You have a headache.
- It's the way you feel after
being at the bar too late.
- Yeah, when you drink too
much, you get a headache.
Yeah.
All right, let's take a look
at our next word, sore throat.
- Sore throat.
So basically, we have two words here.
Let's look at the first one, sore.
- Herding.
- It hurts, right?
- Yep.
- And your throat is-- - Well, it's
the part right here where the bat,
oh, you can't see me.
(laughs)
Well, it's the part at the back of your
mouth that goes down to your stomach.
- All right, that's your throat.
- Yeah.
- So you use your throat to swallow.
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay, now we can use the word sore with different body parts, right?
- Yeah, like a sore back.
- A sore back, right?
Or maybe you were
playing tennis all weekend,
so you have a sore
arm, or even a sore neck.
- Right.
So the word sore, let's take a
look at our third word, runny nose.
- Runny nose.
This is a very strange word.
- I know.
- But it doesn't mean that
your nose is running, right?
- No, but, okay, no, but
when you have a runny nose,
there's lots of water coming
out of your nose, right?
- Right.
- So it's interesting though, because
when you run, you go fast, right?
- So a lot of water is
coming fast out of your nose.
- Out of your nose, runny nose.
- Yeah.
- Okay, our fourth word
today, slightly feverish,
slightly feverish, slightly
feverish, slightly feverish.
- So again, slightly is a little bit.
- A little bit, right, a
little bit, and feverish.
- Well, let's break this word down.
We know fever, right?
- Mm-hmm.
- So when your body is very,
very hot, because you're sick.
- Right.
- So feverish is the feeling of
your body being very, very hot.
- Mm-hmm, okay, so you
have a high temperature.
- It's not that you have
a high temperature,
you have a high temperature, but you
feel like you have a high temperature.
- Okay, so slightly feverish.
- Mm-hmm.
- And our last word, to recover.
- Recover.
- So this means to get better, right?
- Exactly.
- Can you only use it when you're sick?
- So when you recover,
you get better and you rest.
So maybe you can say,
I was so busy this week.
I need to recover this weekend.
- Okay, so yeah, if you feel tired,
you feel sick, you can recover.
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay, let's listen to our dialogue again,
and we can listen to these
words that we've just talked about.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, Daniel speaking, how may help you?
- Hi, Daniel.
Julie here.
(laughs)
- Oh, hi, Julie, how are you?
- Actually, I'm feeling quite ill today.
- Oh, I'm sorry to hear that, what's wrong?
- Oh, I think I'm coming down with the flu.
I have a headache, a sore throat, a runny
nose, and I'm feeling slightly feverish.
- I see, so you're calling in sick.
- Yes, I was hoping to
take the day off to recover.
- Okay, then, try and get some rest.
(upbeat music)
- In this dialogue, we listen to
some really interesting phrases
of how you can tell your boss
that you are feeling sick, right?
- Yeah, some great phrases.
So let's look at these in fluency builder.
- Fluency builder.
- Okay, let's take a look at our
first phrase on fluency builder.
I'm coming down with.
- I'm coming down with.
- All right, so let's
listen to some examples,
and then we'll come back and
explain this interesting phrase.
- Example one.
- My throat really hurts.
I think I'm coming down with a cold.
- Example two.
- You have a runny nose.
Are you coming down with the flu?
- Example three.
- I don't feel well.
I think I'm coming down with something.
- Okay, so basically
coming down with means.
- Starting to get sick.
- I'm beginning to feel sick.
- Yes.
- Okay, so you can use it with.
I'm coming down with the flu.
- I'm coming down with a cold.
- Mm-hmm.
- I'm coming down with a cough.
- Yeah, or I'm coming down with something.
- With something, you
don't know what it is.
- Exactly.
- Okay, let's take a look
at our second phrase.
Calling in sick.
- Calling in sick.
- Okay, calling in sick.
- So this phrase is great.
You know, when you say I'm calling in sick,
you're saying, hey, I'm not going to
come to work today because I am sick.
- Okay, so literally it
means that you call your
office and you say
you're not going to work.
- Yes, but it's great 'cause it's three
words that show such a long idea.
- Right, because otherwise
you would have to say,
I'm calling because I don't feel
well, so I'm not gonna go to work.
- Yes.
- But if you say I'm calling
in sick, everyone knows.
- Everyone understands that
you're not gonna go to work.
- Yep.
- Okay, now let's take
a look at our last phrase.
Take the day off.
- Take the day off.
Now this is a great phrase.
To take the day off is to.
- Not go to work on that day.
- Yes.
- Now you can say, take the week off.
- Take the month off.
- Take the month off or take the year off.
- If you are so lucky.
- All right, so take the day off
means to not go to work on that day.
- All right, let's listen to
our dialogue again now
and then we'll come back
and talk a little bit more.
(upbeat music)
- Hello, Daniel speaking,
how might help you?
- Hi, Daniel.
Julie, hey.
(laughing)
- Well, hi, Julie, how are you?
- Actually, I'm feeling quite ill today.
- Oh, I'm sorry to hear that.
What's wrong?
- I think I'm coming down with the flu.
- I have a headache, a sore throat, a runny
nose, and I'm feeling slightly feverish.
- See, so you're calling in sick.
- Yes, I was hoping to
take the day off to recover.
- Okay, then, try and get some rest.
(upbeat music)
- Well, Marco, have you
ever done what Julie did?
Did you ever call your boss to say
you're sick when you're not really?
- Yeah, of course.
I mean, sometimes you just don't
feel very well, but you're not really sick.
You just don't feel like going to work.
- Yes.
- Or sometimes you have
something to do, right?
- Yep, you know what,
we call those in Canada.
We call them personal days.
- Personal days.
- Yeah.
- So you say, oh, I'm
gonna take a personal day.
- Oh, I'm gonna call in
sick, but then go shopping.
(laughing)
- We used to do that a lot because, for
example, soccer games are such a big deal.
- Oh, yeah.
- And, you know, sometimes
you would have a soccer match
between, I don't know, Brazil, and it
would be maybe at 10 a.m. or 11 a.m.
so everyone would call in sick on that day.
- Yeah, so the boss at least could
plan that he would have an empty office.
- Yeah, or sometimes you
would take half the day off.
So you would just go, you
say, well, I'm not gonna make
it in the morning, but I'll
come in in the afternoon.
- So you would recover very quickly.
- Yeah.
(laughing)
- I'm feeling a little
bit sick, but I'm going
to be better and you
have to know, all right.
So, well, if you have any questions or
comments, please come to our website
and if you have any calling in
six stories, please let us know.
- Yes, you can visit
us at EnglishPod.
com and Marco and I are always
there to answer your questions.
- All right, folks, so
we'll see you next time.
- Thanks for listening, goodbye.
(upbeat music)